So we will, exam is an hour and a half.
There's 15 questions.
I have lots of scrap paper.
There's actually scrap paper on the back of the exam.
I'm going to start to pass out the exam papers.
You can write your name, but don't open the contents, don't open the inside yet.
Sure.
Thank you.
We have the backpacks on the floor, please.
Sure.
Thank you.
All right.
So write your names now, but don't open the exam yet.
And I will start a timer and I'll call out the amount of time remaining as we go.
I'm not too lost in the code I'm writing.
Alright, everybody ready?
was addressed already after the exam is there lecture too yeah there is lecture tonight i said
that before um but i missed it uh so yeah so we'll do the exam it's like an hour and a half by the
time we're done it's usually about we usually it was like a break afterwards and 15 minutes
um you may be done early so you get a longer break and then at about 7 30 7 35 we'll start
the lecture. So, right. Any other questions? I don't answer questions during the exam about
the content. There are lots of students who are taking the exam remotely or in proctoring
and it's not fair that you know we don't want to give people an unfair advantage so we're
just going to keep it this way. So if you need more scrap paper just raise your hand
I'll bring it to you and any other questions. Hey you can begin.
Let's take a look.
so
Alright, so...
I'm going to make a new recipe for my favorite recipe.
I'll show you the recipe for a while.
I'll make a recipe for a few minutes.
So...
Let's go into the pot.
I could have put it in the middle of this video.
I like to make sure that this is good, but it's not really good.
It's great.
I'm going to make the same thing out.
I'm going to make a lot of cool things.
I'm going to make a lot of cool things and I'm going to make a lot of cool things.
so
and now I'm going to make a little bit of a cake and I'm going to make a cake so that I'm going to make a cake.
Now I'm going to make a cake and then I'm going to make a cake.
I'm going to make a cake.
We'll make the top of the top.
Thank you.
Reef the
I have to go ahead and show the stress on the diet.
I'll put it in a little bit.
It will be a little bit too.
I'll go ahead and fry it.
I'm going to fry it in the pan.
This is the favorite part.
and they are very easy to do with them.
If you want to make a video,
you can see the video on the video.
Now, I'm going to put a video on some other video.
And if you want to make a video on this video,
I will see you on the video.
Bye.
Now I'm going to do a little bit of a bag of paper.
so
This is a really good thing.
It's so good.
I love you.
Okay.
Recibly
I'll be able to do the next week.
I'll be able to do the best.
I did it.
I'm going to stay with my face.
I'm going to go ahead and get into the kitchen.
I'll go ahead and get a bit of the kitchen.
I have to use the kitchen.
I will use the kitchen.
It's a kitchen.
I'll cook it for my day.
Let's put the milk on the top.
Let's do this.
I love you.
I'll show you how you do it.
The first time I'm going to use the recipe I have to use the recipe for my videos, I can use the recipe for the recipe for two months.
So, I'm going to use the recipe for two minutes.
I use the recipe for two minutes.
so
This time it's like a little bit more.
The other thing is that the butter and butter is the end.
Gently, this is the end.
This is a very strong butter.
This is the end.
It's very strong.
I'm going to throw it in the bag.
I'll come in.
I'm going to make it better.
This is the hot sauce.
so
So I'm going to do a bit of a little bit about the
churray.
This is a little bit about half of my
and you can always use a candle to warm up.
So let's start.
I love you guys.
Ok.
I think it's a bit of a good time to eat.
I don't know if I'm going to eat here.
I will eat it.
I'm going to eat it right now.
I'm going to eat it.
I don't know if I'm going to eat it.
This is good.
I don't want to eat it.
This is the one that is out there, but it's not easy to use.
It's not easy to use.
I'm going to put on a plate of the lid.
I'm going to put on the plate of the lid on the lid.
I'm going to put on the plate of the lid and put the lid on the lid.
I'm going to put on the plate of the lid.
Let's do it.
So, let's go to the end of the week.
I can't wait to see the pan.
and then we would have to prepare a cup of tea.
And then we would have to prepare for a cup.
So now I'm going to prepare for a cup of tea.
I'm going to have a cup of tea and tea.
I'm going to use a cup of tea.
I'm going to prepare for a cup of tea.
So I'm going to prepare for a cup of tea.
so
After that, I got a good job.
I'm going to go ahead and talk about it.
so
I'm going to make a piece of it.
It's so good.
I'm going to plant it up a bit.
This is so good.
Finally, eating the food and the food is very tasty.
It is delicious!
This is the one that is delicious!
It has to be delicious.
I have my favorite food.
It is delicious!
so
I'm going to try to see the other one.
So, let's get started.
Here we go.
and there is a little bit of water that you can use.
But, it is a very beautiful place.
I think it is very beautiful.
I'll put the water on my way.
I really love that.
so
I'm going to go ahead and put it.
So, you can get the present inside.
Now, how can you do that?
Well, you can get the present inside.
So, I'm going to take a look at the present inside.
I'm going to take a look at the present inside.
So, we do have a present in a present present.
So, here we are going to take a look at the instructions.
So, here we are going to see how it looks like the instructions are going to be in the next video.
I'm going to get very close to the bottom.
I'll get the bottom.
I'm going to get the bottom.
Thank you.
I'll use the oil in the pot.
I'll use the oil.
So, let's see.
so
it
I'll put the six in the bag.
There we go.
The next one.
I'll put the six in the bag.
the
I think it's not the first time I'm using the machine, but I'm not sure if I can do it.
I'm using the machine and the machine.
It's a little bit more.
so
I'm going to make that a little bit of water.
I want to make that a little bit of water.
I don't know.
I'm going to make that a little bit of water.
I want to make that a little bit of water.
I think that's my best.
So...
This is a video of my favorite video.
I'm going to show you how to eat the best.
All right.
The next dish for the chicken, is the turn of the chicken.
The chicken is very well cooked.
If you have a chicken or chicken, it will be nice to use the chicken.
You can always cook your chicken with their chicken.
We also have a lot of hot water.
This is a hot water-like.
I like that with the heat.
.
I'll be taking it here.
The second one is the B-5.
The first one is the B-5.
So...
so
Thank you.
This is a very cool day.
I'll show you how to get a cake.
Let's go to the background of the room.
So, let's take a look at the edge of the edge of the edge of the edge.
Now, I will start my head to the edge of the edge of the edge of the edge.
We will cook the pot while we use the pot.
We will cook the pot.
You can cook the pot.
so
So, it's not working.
All right.
I love you too.
Thank you.
I'm sure I'm going to have the top of the bag I brought.
I'm sure I'm going to have to take a moment for you.
I'm going to have to take a moment for you.
This is my first time.
I'm going to have the top of the bag.
My favorite bag of bag is that I'm going to have to take a moment.
so
One, two, three, four, five, four.
One, two, three, four.
One, two, three.
One, three, four.
I hope you enjoyed it.
Thank you.
One, two, three.
I don't know.
with a break.
With a break.
45 minutes remaining.
I still have a lot of food.
I want the other one to play.
this
I'm gonna use this video.
so
OK.
All right.
I will cut it up.
I'll do the same thing.
I will cut it out.
I'll take the next step.
so
All right.
So, let's get started.
I'm going to try to make a little bit more of this.
I'm going to use this machine to get it.
I'm going to use this machine.
I'm going to use it.
and make sure that you are using it as a tool.
I will make sure that you can use it as a tool to use it.
It is a tool to use a tool to use it as a tool to use.
I will use it as a tool to use it as a tool to use it as a tool to use it.
Tune out.
...
so
I did a lot of things but I was going to say,
I don't know what to do.
It's not going to be a bit better.
I don't know.
All right.
Thanks.
So, I'm going to go ahead and roll it.
this
This is a good one.
Next time, the product is called the product.
We'll give a look at the product.
This is the product.
I'll be looking at the product.
I'll just show you how to use a product.
the
so
So, let's do it.
I'm gonna go ahead and go.
I think I'm going to use this for a couple of years.
What do you think about this?
I'm just gonna try it out.
I'm just gonna touch it.
I'm gonna touch it.
I think I'm gonna touch it.
I think I'll touch it.
It's okay.
So
so
Take a look at the top and see what you see in the top.
All right, let's do this.
About a half an hour, right?
All right.
You can now see what the other person has to do with the same aspect.
You can see what the other person has to do with the other person.
I think we are still trying to find out how to make an example of how to make an example of how to make an example of what I'm going to do.
I think I'm going to get the other person.
I'll have to point the point where you will see how to make an example of how to make an example of how to make an example of how to make an example of how to make an example.
So, I'm going to put a little bit of a hand in the middle.
I'm going to put it in my hand.
I'm going to put a little bit of a camera on the side.
You can see the camera's camera's camera.
I'll take my hand if you want to.
so
So, once you're using the chocolate, you can make it a little better.
This is a little better.
Let's make the chocolate.
It's a little better.
I really like that.
So, let's go.
That was the chocolate.
It was a little better.
It's a little better.
The chocolate.
It's better.
So, let's go.
Let's go.
Thank you.
Okay.
Next time I put the
We just did it.
so
Okay.
Thank you.
And if you like to make a little more you can also use to make a little more
This will be perfect for you in a good place
You can also use the same kind of work
After your time, you can use the same kind of work
I also use the same kind of work
You can use it to make a little more work
You can use the same kind of work
If you use the same kind of work
Thank you.
So this is a very popular thing that I like to do so I like the reason why I like the other thing.
Now I'm going to start taking a break.
I think that I'm going to be a little bit more on the other side of the side of the side of the side.
I'm going to start with this one.
I'll start with the next one.
This is the best way to cross the line.
This is a beautiful color.
I'm not sure how to do it.
I'm not sure how to cross the line.
I'm not sure how to move it.
So, it's not too much.
...
Thank you.
So, let's go.
The pattern of the wood is not available, so it's not enough weight.
So it's not enough to be able to pull it into the same way.
As you can see, I'm going to work with a little bit more complex.
So, the pattern is when the pattern is not about the same.
I took the same time to eat.
I think
I just put on a plate.
I can't get it!
Here we go.
It's not going to be a perfect for being here, but it can be better for being here.
It's not going to be a perfect for being here.
So, I'm going to show you a little bit.
And now you can see it.
so
So, let's take a look at the next week.
Thank you.
I'm going to take the cover again.
I don't know what to do.
I don't know.
I like the other side.
The final part is to make sure the ingredients are so easy to keep in mind.
But I would like to thank the ingredients for being in the room.
Thank you.
Let's go.
I'll be right back.
If you want to make sure that you don't need to know what you want.
If you want to make sure that you don't need to like how you do the exact same thing you're going to need.
I don't need to know how to use that.
I also want to make sure that you don't need to know how to use that.
There are a lot of fruits in the world.
This is a nice taste of a food.
I like this.
I like this, but it's still very nice.
I like this food.
I like that food.
I'm not sure how you can do it.
I want to use the same color to the color.
The color of the color is a little more.
I am using this color to all the color.
I will make my mouth open.
All right.
I think that's how I to use this.
I think that's what I want to do.
I can use the same trick in the left side.
I think I should use this trick,
And, so, I'm going to just start counting here.
So, this is the same.
...
All right.
Alright.
Thank you.
Yes.
so
.
So 15 minutes from now, we'll start the lecture.
I'll try it.
This is the same size of the size of the size of the size of the size.
to get the same on your own way.
I can see there's a little bit of a negative effect, as it comes to the middle side, but the next one, is the object.
I'm going to show you how to do this.
Shh.
I'm going to let you know when I'm going to put on the right hand side.
I'm going to put a little bit on the right hand side.
So, let's see how the
that's not a good idea.
See you next time.
Thank you.
So, this is the first time it's time to come to the room.
So, you can see this is the same group.
So, this is the third time.
I know that the time I'm going to be using this to make sure that it's in the room.
I'm going to pick up this up and I'll give you a few minutes.
I'm going to go to the room with it, but it's time to get started.
Get your hand out of the bag.
Let's go.
It's a big deal.
I love it.
I'm a big deal.
And now I am going to put a knife with a knife and I will be able to fix it.
I will just get it.
I will just start looking for this knife.
You can put it in your mouth.
I will just start drawing a knife.
Look out.
This is a semi-pensile.
I'm going to use the same for the first time.
I have a lot of water.
I'm going to go out and get a little bit more and a little bit more.
I'm going to go out and let this one out.
I'm going to go out and get some water and water.
do
I'll give it a little more.
I'm going to go ahead and get it here.
I'm going to go ahead and hit it.
so
I'll wait for it.
It is good to have you here.
I'm going to try to cook it.
I'm not going to cook it.
so
I'm going to put it up.
Let's go.
This is a very different color.
This is a little bit more.
Just a little bit more.
You can see a little bit more.
I'm going to go ahead and grab it.
I don't.
I will use the light to say, and I will use the light to say, and then I will use the light to say, and then the light to say, and then the light to say, and then the light to say, and then the light to say, and then the light to say, and then the light to say, and then the light to say, and then the light to say, and then the light to say, and then the light to say, and then the light to say, and then the light to say, and then the light to say, and then the light to say, and then the light to say, and then the light to say, and then the light to say, and then the light to say, and then the light to say, and then the light to say, and then the light to say, and then the light to say, and then the light to say, and then the light to say, and then the light to say, and then the light to say, and then the light to say, and then the light to say,
This is the first time I took the two steps, and I would like to take the two steps to go.
I have to keep this front.
I'm sorry.
So, what are the words that you use?
Well, it's a very simple, and I don't want to use it.
I think we can use it.
All right.
So I think I should do it.
I love you.
I've been listening to this episode of the game, and I'm listening to this episode of
You make it.
Please press the bell button, and press the bell button.
So, I'll use the bell button.
Now, press the bell button.
It's the bell button.
I would like to know that I'm going to go back to the table.
I'm going to be by the top of the table.
But it's a bit like it's just a big deal.
I'm going to be someplace like this.
I'm going to be using this table because I'm going to be using this table.
I'm going to be using this table.
What is this?
Let's get started.
All right.
Well, I'm going to get started.
So I should have the exams graded either tomorrow or Thursday.
The next two nights are going to be a lot of grading to catch up on.
I've got your study guides to do who I have to review the grader homework for.
so I've heard you integrated it.
So that will be the next couple of days.
So you should know what your exam rate is
by Thursday night.
That's my plan.
Let's see.
Next week, I will be traveling on business.
I'm actually leaving Tuesday.
So what we'll do is I'm going to do office hours
on Monday instead of Tuesday.
sorry, instead of Wednesday. So I'll send email with all of this. It'll be clear, but
the Wednesday office hours will go to Monday and I might move the Tuesday office hours, but I,
it may be better to split it up and do some on Tuesday before class like usual.
Normally, I haven't had a lot of folks coming for office hours, but normally when the exam goes back,
when the grades go out, y'all want to know.
I will not be able to carry all the exams with me.
So those of you who took the exam basically in the classroom,
I'm not going to be carting them around,
and I won't have an image of them on my computer.
So if you want to know how you did on specific questions,
we can cover that in class when I'm back,
like before class, like office hours when I'm back.
I don't give back.
I have actually two trips.
I'm going business trip, then I fly back, then I have a wedding in Colorado.
So it's like I'm all over the place next week.
So best bet will be to do that when we're here.
If any of you are watching this remotely and you took the exam through proctoring,
I will have an image of your exam on my computer because I have to download it all.
So it's on this computer and then it will be with me so I can then look at what you did.
So for next week's office hours, if you do the exam through remote proctoring or through DePaul proctoring on site, we can talk about your exam next week.
Specifically, we can see your exam.
I'm just not going to scan on all these pages.
All right.
So that will be next week.
And class will be on Zoom.
So instead of don't come to the classroom, I'll make sure this is published as well.
Don't come to the classroom.
everybody can attend class on Zoom next week, no matter what section you're in.
Please make sure I remember to hit record. If somebody interrupt me if I'm
starting at 545 and I don't hit record. So, for those of you who like to watch
the lecture through course online next week, it will be recording this room with
nothing going on in it. So, for next week only, there will be a recording that I
will share with you of the live class that we had on zoom. It will be through you watch it
through zoom and hopefully that will work out okay so that'll be the plan. The good thing about that
is I will have my pen display which I can connect to this thing and I can whiteboard on that thing
and last quarter I used it the whole quarter because my shoulder I had shoulder surgery
and I couldn't do this so I know it works very well so those of you who be
on zoom or whether watching the recording or just during the live class
you should be able to see everything whiteboard wise it'll be all on my
shared screen so then you can pause the recording while you're watching it if
you want to stop and look all right so any questions about any of that that's
just next week only there's some important projects at work and normally
I don't like to travel when I teach, but my boss and I had a discussion and so I was like,
well, all right, I'll teach remotely for one class for this quarter, so I can participate
in these important meetings.
Okay.
All right, anything on that?
All right, cool.
Again, all of it's going to be in email to you, so you'll have, I'll make it nice and
clear.
You'll have all the outline of what's going on and the guidelines, and we'll go from
there.
All right, and feel free, Discord is your friend, so send me a message on Discord if you have specific questions.
I will ask that if you want to meet during office hours, you send me a message on Discord just so I don't expect you.
And, yeah, the Wednesday office hours I have to cancel because there's work dinners and things like that.
So it's just kind of moving.
All right, cool.
All right, so we're on week six.
We just finished our midterm.
We've got three topics tonight, should pretty much cover the rest of the evening, the time
that we have together.
And these items are sort of related.
We're starting to get into some more and more advanced topics with programming languages.
So, we'll start with L values.
So I'll be honest, when I first started teaching this, I forgot what an L value was.
I had to go look it up because it's one of those things that they talk about in academic land,
but when you're a professional programmer this is not a common thing we discuss.
So, it's actually not hard. At first I was like, what the heck is that?
When I read it, I was like, okay, now I understand.
So, we're thinking about when we read and write to a memory location.
So, what do we read or sorry, when do we read and when do we write to a memory location?
And spoiler alert, L values, R values,
essentially what we're talking about,
and this is oversimplifying,
but if you have some kind of expression or statement,
like this is the left and this is the right,
because it's the left side of the equal sign
and the right side of the equal sign.
So that's where the term L values and R values come from.
So, demystifying that. Now this isn't strictly
all of it, but you can start to think about it in this way.
So if I have this declaration,
I have a mutable variable x
and its type is int, and I set its value to 0,
what does x mean in this next expression here?
There's a couple different ways you can slice it.
What does x mean?
0.
x means 0.
Okay.
So Dylan, that is what...that's great.
That's true.
It's not false.
But now what we're trying to do is we're trying to break up this.
We're studying programming.
So we're breaking this up.
So x.
What does x mean?
X appears how many times?
And it means two different things, right?
Because you know what this is doing.
What's it doing?
what is this code doing? Adding one. So it's taking the value from x, adding one, and then
updating x. So x has two meanings. You're reading, so it's an r value, and you're writing,
that's an l value. So this is what we do when we study programming languages. We break it
down into this minutiae of detail that we always gloss over when we're just doing programming.
So, right hand X denotes the value as being read from some storage location, and left hand X denotes the storage location itself, or you can think of this as an address.
Not strictly literally an address like in C, but it refers to some place in memory that you're updating.
So, this terminology goes back to this person named Strayke.
I think it's, yeah, Christopher Strakey from, and I don't know if I'm not,
I don't know if I'm pronouncing that right.
But that would be how I think of pronouncing that.
So he apparently published a paper in 1967,
called Fundamental Concepts in Programming Languages.
And so, because he was talking about programming languages and
translating codes written by humans into something a computer can use.
he started to break it down and define this terminology.
And you can actually click this here if you want.
It will take you to Springer,
this must be the publisher.
And it looks like this might be a different version of it
or a later edition.
Oh yeah, it does have 1967.
Ok. So Professor Mitch, who I work closely with on this course, studies programming languages
in his PhD work. Or not so much his PhD work, he's done with that, but I mean his research
as a professor. And so he thinks about this probably all the time, where I'm not thinking
about this because I go to work and I write code, and I do all this stuff really fast,
As do you, because you're all programmers by now.
And we're just introducing you to breaking this up
into the smaller bits, to think about what the meaning is.
All right.
So, expression for which L-mode evaluation succeeds,
so that's what an L-value is, L-mode evaluation,
is kind of like, this is almost like defining a term
by using the term, right?
But, effectively means it has an address,
It has a place in memory that you're updating.
So in C, an L value, quite literally, hasn't had Riz.
So we have these assignment statements in C.
X is going to refer to someplace on the stack, most likely,
if you're inside of a function.
Typically in C, you're inside of a function.
Same thing with Y.
P is going to be a pointer to an int.
and the pointer itself is on the stack but the actual place that it's pointing to is not.
And then you have this business here, so here we have a double D referencing going on,
so R is a pointer to a pointer to an int, C starts getting very symbolic very fast.
So in Scala, we can assign two L values. So we have x, l, here in this one we have a and b, this is a tuple, right? And then we have this pattern match, or this I guess, it's sort of, oh sorry, it's not a pattern match, we use the same syntax for pattern match.
Here what we have is we're basically saying we're creating a list and we're assigning y and z.
Oh, no.
I got my l's and r's mixed up, right?
So what's happening here is we're actually constructing a list, right?
So we're constructing a list and it's got y at the head and then z is the next element,
the head of the tail, if you will, and then new.
And, all right, so because it's doing this, it is an L value because it's taking this
list L that we have over here, and it's binding the one to the Y and the two to the Z.
Boy I flopped that one.
But you can see what it's doing.
It is a pattern match because it's taking this list and it's binding,
it's matching this one and saying, yeah, I got one element,
then I got another element, and then I got an empty list.
So these are yellow values.
It's not an orange value.
In fact, if I remember to read what's above,
then I won't say the wrong.
All right, so we can create formal semantics
to express what this means.
So in formal semantics, this is the content
of our immutable data stores, or I'm sorry, variable stores,
variable stores.
So here we have this assignment, we have an expression,
we're assigning it to x.
We have this xi, which contains our variables.
And if we have our expression and it produces a value,
then this assignment is gonna produce a value.
This is our equal, our assignment rule, sorry our assignment rule.
So we go from xi 0 to xi 1, and
we've updated x to now have the value v.
value be. So the content of our mutable stores,
basically the names of the variables in our mutable stores.
So what is not an L Mode?
So L Mode evaluation is sometimes disallowed.
So in C, we can't take an address of temporary expression.
So here you can take X and Y.
And you can add them, and then you can try to get the address of that temporary location.
Because if you do this addition, it's storing it somewhere.
And then trying to get the address of that is going to fail.
That won't compile.
That's not allowed.
If I try to take X plus Y and assign whatever that...
So if I have done the X plus Y and stored it somewhere in memory,
I can't just put a seven in that place in memory.
with an expression there.
With that same.
So that's not allowed, that won't compile.
And that makes sense, right?
If you think about that link,
you're like, what does that mean, right?
So x plus y is not an L value.
Although it might be stored temporarily.
So more on L values.
You might have to do what's called R mode evaluation.
So you might have to think about
So here's an array access in C or Java.
So here if you're doing this array access, you actually have to do this computation here and
somehow that's going to get stored somewhere.
And then you use that to access the array.
And then you're updating that location in the array.
So this whole thing here is an L value, right?
But you have to do an R value here, you have to evaluate this thing,
this part here, in order to figure out where it is.
And the same thing with field access.
So if you have some object, you have a reference to an object.
You have to actually, internally it has to de-reference that object to get
to the place where it can now update the F1 of that object, right?
So that's it for L values and R values.
There's only seven slides for this, so it's not too complicated.
L values, you are writing to someplace in memory.
In C, you can take an address.
So we have this ampersand operator,
so you can get to the address of something.
In Scala, in Java, they're assignable.
So if I have x, I can update x to have 5.
Actually, here I'm declaring x, and I'm setting it equal to 5.
And then here I have my list one, two, three, and
I'm deconstructing that list into y and tail.
So y will have one, and tail will have a list that contains two and three,
and then nil at the end.
It's not nil as a separate element, but nil as the tail of that tail, right?
But you might need to do an R-mode evaluation to then get to
the point where you can do the assignment of .
So rvalues, you read a value at a memory location.
So this is all about reading and writing.
In C, Scala, Java, you have expressions like x, 1, x plus y.
You have to evaluate these expressions
in order to get some value to store.
So there's a link here.
There's specialized uses of L value and R value.
And that's not going to work.
It looks like I have lost my internet.
Or Cloud Flare doesn't like me.
Yeah, so there.
The following expressions are L value,
so this kind of goes through some more
development of these things.
This looks like it's C++, C++ language reference.
That's it for L values and R values.
So now we're gonna talk about something a little bit more
meaning called argument passing.
So we're going to talk about how arguments to functions
should be passed in.
And this is somewhat related to L values and R values.
It's useful to think about it.
Because if you're passing a variable into a function
or an argument into a function, when
you're creating that new variable inside the function
that's holding whatever you passed in,
it's actually assigning.
Even though you did write that, you wrote the function
and then you called the function.
but it's actually creating a place in memory and
then putting that value in that place in memory.
So you'll write it, so that's an L value.
So just keep that.
All right, so we'll talk about call by value and call by reference.
We've already talked about call by name.
Those are the three, essentially the three ways to do argument passing in any work.
So here's some code,
we have a function f, and we have a next step,
x, y are parameters going into f,
and then we ask what are x, y,
and then we call f,
we pass hello, and then we pass 10.
So what are x, y, hello,
and 10 below?
So what we call these things are,
x and y are called formal parameters,
or sometimes we just simply say they're parameters.
So actually, the only one at my job who whenever people use
the words arguments and parameters,
I'm always correcting everybody
because I think I'm the only one
that has a masters in CS on my team.
These are formal parameters
because they're declared as parameters to the function.
And then hello and 10 are actual parameters.
That's what's used in the literature.
I usually just simplify and use the word arguments.
So, when you call a function,
you're passing arguments into a function,
But when the function is executing,
you talk about the parameters into the function,
the parameters of the function.
So that's just the semantics that we use
when we're talking about these things.
Okay, so what does a call to f print here?
Anybody wanna, this is Scala,
does anybody want to take a guess?
Can we talk through it?
I call f.
I have a variable x.
It's mutable, right?
And I set it equal to 1.
I set the value.
2,1.
And I call g.
You're saying 2?
Yeah.
So I call G, and G executes.
So it has a Y, right?
It updates Y to get Y plus one.
So now, Y is going to contain two, right?
And then I come out of G. And then what happens?
What does my X have in it?
So you think it's two.
You think it's two?
You think it's one now?
Yeah.
You change your answer.
No, I mean in G it's 2.
In G it's 2, but the question I asked was what's printed?
Oh, you didn't print it?
So it's 1.
So it is 1 and the reason why is because Scala by default uses callbyvalue.
So what that means is that we're actually passing a copy of the data that's stored in
X into G, and then we have a new,
we have new storage over here declared on the stack,
and we update, oh and actually this is kind of weird, right?
Because this would have to say bar.
I'm not even sure this would be valid
because I think by default these are valid.
I don't even know if this is file.
So it could be a bad example.
But you get what it's getting at, right?
Like if you could do this statement, right?
Sorry, if you could do this expression,
then you would be updating this local source here.
OK.
So I did not actually test a scene, whether it compiles.
So this will print one, as we said.
Because Scala is going to use callByValue.
Actually, now I have to test it.
It's going to bother me, right?
So I'm gonna copy it and I'm gonna bring it over to the repl.
I can type this one.
Yep, I didn't think so.
Cuz that's gonna be a valve automatically.
I think you can, I don't usually use VARs.
I think you would need to change this.
Oops, let's see if that works.
Nope, it doesn't like that.
So this example is weird.
I would have to do something like mess up the example.
So in Java, though, if we wrote this in Java,
and you didn't declare this as final,
you would get call by value.
So it would make a copy, and that's the key.
You're getting a copy.
Most programming languages are going to use call-by-value by default.
So my first language was C, then I did C++, then I did Java, which is also call-by-value.
People don't think it is, but we'll talk about one.
Call-by-reference, so some programming languages are going to use call-by-reference.
So call by value when we run g of e, we have to evaluate e to a value v, right.
And then we pass a copy of the value v to g, and then the call e,
this is expressed, changes to copy of v are not visible to them.
Oh, callee changes.
Right.
So when you call the function g, if g is making any changes
to that storage, they're not visible outside of g.
So that's call by value.
So you're always giving your call.
Call by reference, though, to run g of e,
you evaluate e to an l value r.
Then you pass the address r.
So here you're passing the address of R to G, and then as the callee,
the code you called, changes that variable,
those changes will be visible to the caller.
So the way to understand this is if you take the simple example of
Let's use Java.
So if I say f int x, and then I say x equals x plus 1.
You know, as programmers working with Java, you're getting a copy of x, right?
So if you path, you call f of three.
Well, actually, if you have out here int y equals three.
Then you call f of y.
Doing this increment doesn't change y, right?
You know that.
And the way that works internally is that a copy is made.
Now, if we did something like to find,
I'll use something straight out of the Java.
Let's say I have atomic and x,
I can't remember what,
so I think I have to say x.increment but I can't remember.
Pretend that this works.
this compiles and it does what we think it does.
So if I do that, if I have atomic heat line equals ..
Let's just say it goes up.
And then I say f of y.
What actually happens is, when I've allocated this new atomic int,
I have this thing, and I have y pointing to it.
And then when I pass this into here,
And on the stack, I have a new stack frame.
I'm building my stack down this time.
I have a new stack frame.
X is going to point.
Oh, sorry.
X is going to point to there.
And actually, this is actually not correct.
Let me fix that.
So let's do that all the time.
So I have a heap allocated atomic.
And so my box for atomic int is here.
and then on my stack I'll build my stack going up this so I'm out here in this
main code mean I'm just gonna call this the program and I have a reference called
y pointing to this thing and when I call F then I have a reference X pointing to
the same thing and that's that is actually you're passing a reference so
So it's a little confusing, because you think it's called by reference based on what I just
said, but what actually happens is it's called by value, because when it passes Y, it's actually
making a copy of the address into this reference type here.
So that's why technically Java is called by value, even though it's like simulating call
by reference.
Okay, so.
But it behaves like call by reference?
Yes, go ahead.
behaves like call by reference?
I can't hear you.
So like it behaves like call by reference?
Yes.
It seems like it's called by reference to you,
but because of the way it's actually
allocating storage on the stack and copying the data
that refers to the address, the data that holds the address,
that makes it call by value.
And it works that way because Java, what did I want to say?
It works that way because of the meaning of reference types in Java.
Like, they've abstracted that into the type system.
Hopefully that makes sense.
So, yes.
So, call by value, you're making copies.
call by reference, you're actually passing a reference.
So here's an example.
In this example, we're going to be somewhat contrived.
We're going to pretend this is Scala-like,
and this is not actually Scala because, again, we're updating y.
So in a call by value language,
this will print one as we just saw in the previous set of material.
And then if we made this call by reference,
it would print 2, so let's think about why.
If this is called by reference when I'm calling g,
I'm actually passing a reference to x.
And so that's storage that I've allocated here in this stack frame,
and I'm passing a reference back to the other stack frame.
We don't actually do that in Skellar.
So here, when we increment, if this were a reference to the same memory, then when we
exit G, then we would see the change that we made, because we're changing that other
place in memory, so we're used to thinking about this thing, and later on it'll say,
we simulate call by reference in Java.
OK, now we're going to look at formal semantics.
Don't freak out.
There's a lot of mathematical symbols.
So how do we specify what a function does?
So we already have this global store Xi for variables,
and this is actually global variables.
We need another store, Phi,
which maps function names to argument names and function bodies.
So this is just the idea that when you have a function,
and you have a function here,
this is a function named and this will tell you what the argument name is with.
So when you call the function you're passing the arguments, right?
You typically pass it in order.
Some languages like you, Scala actually lets you name the arguments,
but it knows what the names of the variables are,
so what the names of the parameters are.
So when you call the function, and you just say F of Y, it knows to take whatever Y is
and store it in this new thing X.
And it names it X, and it knows that because of what's in V.
You also need a local store row for arguments and local variables.
So before we had Xi, which was just, you know, we were pretty much evaluating these little
programs that were in a single scope.
So I call them global, but they're in the single scope.
So those are all your variables in your program essentially.
Now we're talking about calling a function.
So now we have a separate variable store that's specific to a stack frame.
And then there you have the arguments.
So here we would have an argument, one argument next.
And then if we had, maybe we had int z equals 0 and
then we'd print lines here.
I'm just making up stuff.
No, it's Java, so I have to do, you know what I mean.
I didn't do it, this wouldn't actually work.
But it's Java, so I just created a new thing called z.
This would be in my problem because I declared a new variable inside me.
So here's the rules of the rule for call by value.
So again, always start on the left side of the expression down here.
So we have this expression where we're calling a function,
and we're passing several different expressions as arguments.
Let me say that right, arguments.
And we have to evaluate each one of these.
So if we look at this going up, it'll say,
well, we evaluate each argument E sub n.
So it's evaluating each expression.
And then when we do that, let's see, each time, when we evaluate our expression one becomes
our value one and we do that all the way down to our nth expression.
And each time it's just modifying the global variable store, right?
And there's a phi and then a phi one.
You don't have to memorize this by the way.
So this will always be given to you if you need to see it.
Let's see that there's the values being generated by evaluating expressions.
And then we get to phi .
What this means is, now that I've evaluated each of these in turn,
now I have to call the function, so I have to look up what the function is.
And that will actually have the body, the code body, as well as the variables
you're assigning as you can vote game. And then you have your psi of 0.
Oh yeah, no. This is psi of 0. And then you end up with psi of n. I think there should
be an n there. Again, don't freak out about this. I did not double check and triple check
on the second, because Professor Mitch created the slides.
Then over here we have call by reference.
So this is going to be a little bit different.
It looks very similar.
We have f we're calling with all of these parameters
that we have to evaluate, just like before.
The major difference here is our, over here,
our row is going to be our row of n union.
So this is gonna be like, the row is gonna end up containing all the local
variables union with all the variables that we have when we pass the arguments.
So these represent the parameters inside the function body.
So it's just a little bit different.
Again, this is just to show you what the semantics like look like.
All right, all by reference and temperance.
So can temporary values be passed as L values?
Remember, temporary value is like when you do some sort of evaluation of an expression
and you store it in either in memory somewhere temporarily or in a register.
So can they be passed as L values?
So g of x plus 1 is obviously not legitimate in call by reference, right?
So we're used to call by value, so we would say, oh, well, I have to evaluate x plus 1 first,
then take the result and pass it into g.
In call by reference, this wouldn't really make sense, because you would evaluate this
thing, and you're storing the results of that in a register or in memory somewhere.
And then you're trying to pass a reference to that location, and then you couldn't really
access it.
So it's obviously not really very legitimate.
But some languages will actually allow it.
So the language Scala that we use in C and Java won't let you do this.
Well, Java doesn't have a color of it, so forget it.
And in Scala, we don't have a color.
But Perl, Perl will allow it.
So here's some Perl.
So Perl, I hate this language, by the way.
Practical, Extraction, and Report Language.
It was all the rage 25 years ago,
when I was a student here, or yeah, it was about that.
And it's used for text processing and all kinds of things.
And the only time I've ever seen it since I graduated
was when I came back to teach here and the professor gave me scripts and all.
So I was like, yeah, great.
I didn't have to, luckily I didn't have to do much of this.
So, Perl's gonna use call by reference.
So if I, here's my f, I'm calling f.
So in my function f I have new storage, my x.
I'm setting it equal to one, I call g and
I update this, this is the first parameter.
that's what this means, I take the value, I add one,
I increment, I assign, I come back out,
and I print it, I'm gonna get two.
So this is like that code we saw before.
So, what I did here was,
Perl is gonna allow temporary,
so here, this is changing that.
So again, if we look at the previous slide,
we just passed x, this time we're passing x plus one,
perfectly valid, and call by reference,
So what do we get?
So we have one.
We increment.
And then we pass that to g.
And then we do this increment, so we're passing the reference.
But it's this reference of this temporary location.
We do this increment, we update the temporary location.
We come back here out of g.
And when we look at x, we still have what we had before.
Because we modified some other place in memory.
So this will print out one.
So what most people do when they code Perl
is they simulate call by value by creating copies explicitly.
So if you call G and you immediately do my $Y
and this at underscore thing, it will basically
take that, I guess, in this case,
we only have one parameter, right?
I don't know what it would look like if you had more than one parameter because,
again, I don't do Perl.
But it would then create a local variable Y in your G function.
It would do this update here, it would come back, and
it would still print one.
So most people will simulate call my value by creating this explicit comment.
But I don't know anybody who does Perl anymore.
All right, so in C and when I learned C, we talked about call by reference but we were
actually simulating call by reference, right?
So you explicitly pass, receive, and access a pointer.
So everybody who's done C, it's the biggest headache is pointers and pointer arithmetic,
right?
So I have my main program, I have x and I set it equal to 1, I pass the address of x,
So here I have P as a pointer to an inch, so that all makes sense.
And then I try to print this out.
I'm going to get back.
Because I incremented, I should get 2.
This simulates call by reference.
It's technically call by value because you're passing a pointer.
So it's actually copying the address of x into P on this stack frame.
C++ also has this reference type thing.
You may have seen this.
In C++, if you change this to use this ampersand thing,
then y is a reference to an int.
So if I have my x equals 1 and I call g passing x by reference,
so this is again different than passing a pointer, right?
It goes in here and it increments y, and then it actually updates that original location.
So whatever x is pointing to is also pointing out.
It's not really pointing.
Whatever x, the value that x is referring to.
It's hard to find the right language, but you know what I mean.
It's like I have x, I've passed a reference to x,
I've updated what's in the reference, what I'm referring to, and
And then over here I'm printing it out.
So, unlike the int star syntax that creates references implicitly.
So, the question arises, what makes this design error problem?
So, in C++ the answer is here.
I think that's the same code.
Yeah.
Well, it's the same code but it takes the ampersand off, right?
So, at the caller over here and you call G of X, CBR call by reference is indistinguishable
from call by value.
So, it doesn't look any different.
So you as a programmer looking at this code, you don't see that this is call by reference
because you're not looking at the method signature necessarily.
Sometimes it could be in a completely different file in a library somewhere, right?
So this makes it indistinguishable to you as a programmer and this small change in the
function signature has a very large effect of the caller because it changes the semantics,
it changes the meaning of the program.
So imagine if you upgrade your library to some new version that's introduced different
semantics on the code that you're calling, you're going to potentially get different
behavior than you had before.
So this is a bad design.
So C-sharp deals with this by having reference parameters and actually I'm planning next
week to show you a little bit about Rust, which I'm learning right now.
There's a whole bunch of stuff that Rust does to do with this stuff.
But in C sharp, we have reference parameters, so here you have ref in,
so you have to say ref X when you call to get the reference,
to get this code to compile, actually.
So this is a little bit better because you can look at this code as a programmer and
realize, oh I am passing a reference.
And if this were to change on you, then you wouldn't compile.
So, unlike int ampersand like we had in C++, you have to use this ref keyword in the caller.
So, here this is going to show you passing a non-element.
So in C++, I'm going to get an error here.
So what I've done is, I have an x.
set the value equal to 1, then I'm going to increment x and store that in some temporary
location that I can't really access, passing it, that temporary location, to g.
Because I am passing a reference, this won't compile.
Okay, so now we'll talk about Java.
So Java has a restrictive form of pointers called references.
their reference types. This doesn't mean call by reference. They must point, so references,
as you know, I did this over here, they point to heap allocated objects. They cannot point
to stack allocated data. And they cannot point to primitive types. So if you have a primitive
type like an int or a float or a double or a char or a binary, sorry, a boolean, you
can't pass an address of that storage.
It's just not, you're not able,
you don't have the syntax for it.
They didn't have that .
So Java references cannot be forged.
So that means forged is like when we do print,
pointer arithmetic.
I'm not really up on the terminology, forged,
but I can't take two integers and cast
and then pass a reference to that.
I can't.
Well, like in C, I can take, I can take addresses, and I can store them as hints, and I can
do arithmetic on them and call this.
I can't do that.
So Java references cannot be forged.
So remember in Java you either have a reference type, or you have a permanent type.
And a reference type is always going to point to a heap-allocated object.
And it's called by value in Java because you're passing the contents of the address, like
actual literal address, the numeric value representing the address in memory is actually
copied from one place to another, that's why it's called .
So objects are only accessed via references in Java.
So unlike C++, in C++, you can have these reference types which are something else.
Java has no address of operator, there's no ampersand.
I'm learning Rust right now and this ampersand shows up all over the place and
you never know, you have to like really understand why you're learning Rust.
It has a similar meaning to what C++ had.
But it's throwing me for a loop cuz I've done Java and Scala for
28 years, so 25 years.
All right, so callbyvaluedjava.
we simulate call by reference in Java.
So back to your question from earlier,
we simulate call by reference in Java
because we have this heap allocated object
with a field of intended argument type.
So here's an example.
Oh, actually, this is an example
where we actually simulate
what call by reference looks like.
So this is because Java is call by value.
But what we have to do is we have this int ref
where when we instantiate an instance of intref,
we can update what its variables are, its storage, right?
So if I have in my main program, I have an intref,
and then I set the thing that it's holding to one,
the n value there.
Then I call g, passing an intref.
So this will use call-by-value to pass that address,
But over here in G, G is now this R thing is gonna point to the same thing in memory.
It's very similar to what I drew over here, alright?
It's gonna point to the same thing in memory.
And then in G, it's gonna do this update.
It's gonna say, oh, okay.
Well, I have a reference to this other thing in memory on the heap and
I'm gonna take its n value and increment it and update it, okay?
And then when I get out of here, when G returns,
I can access my intRefS and that memory will have changed.
All right, so here's some call by value in Scala.
So if you look at this code, it takes an X, that's a double,
and it takes those, it takes that X, it actually just does some aliasing here.
It copies x into x1, it copies x into x2, and it does the subtraction.
And hopefully you understand that the value of x1 and
the value of x2, the value that x1 contains and
value of x2 contains are the same.
So subtracting like that gives you 0.
So this will print 0.
It's the difference of the same random double.
Yeah.
What happens if it's called by reference?
Would it not work or something?
If it's called by reference.
Well, we don't really have a call by reference in Scala.
But if it were called by reference,
then what you would be doing is you would evaluate this,
and it would be stored in some temporary location.
And then, the reference to that temporary location
would be passed.
But you're not actually changing it.
so it wouldn't matter, does that make sense.
We're gonna change this now to call by value with passing a function.
So if we pass this function here, this function here is gonna take nothing, right,
to void is the, sorry, it's a unit, I have to use the right terms.
It's Scala, so it's unit.
takes a unit and it executes this code when the function is invoked, right?
So it's going to produce a new random number.
So when I pass x here, that's now a function.
So I'm going to invoke the function twice.
And that means I'm going to get two separate...
This is going to execute two separate times.
It's math.random.
So I have two different random numbers.
I will subtract them and return.
I'm going to get a different random result every time.
So we can emulate that in object-oriented programming like this.
Java has this interface called supplier and
supplier is gonna have a get method.
And because it's a supplier of double, it's gonna return double.
And essentially what this is doing is it's gonna,
every time get is called, it's gonna call math.random and
return the results.
So if I implement my client and I have my g, so
the same as g over there, I'm passing a supplier of a double. Well, that's essentially what
this is, right? You invoke the function, and it just gives you a double. You don't give
it anything. You just invoke the function, and you get a double. So here's my supplier.
I refer to it as t. I call get, so it's going to invoke math.random and return, and I call
get again. A different random number will come back into x2, and then I'll do this subtraction.
So, when I invoke G,
I'm gonna get basically the same result as over here.
So this is what that looks like.
So this is very, very verbose, right, there's a lot.
This is a lot simpler to read and to reason about in my opinion.
This is why I like functional programming.
Java starts to get very tedious to look at.
Okay.
Oh, and what little distinction here?
So here in Java I'm calling new get Rand.
So it's actually constructing a new one of these, right?
And this is the original way Java worked.
Now we have lambdas in Java.
But if I do this, this will satisfy.
This is a lambda.
And it takes void and returns math.random.
And this will satisfy the interface of supplier.
So it will automatically, I think under the covers, I don't remember.
I think lambdas will actually use a different bytecode.
It used to have to actually construct a class internally.
Okay, so call my name, Scala.
So Scala has a special syntax, which we've seen before,
for using Thunks as parameters, and call by name parameters
are non-script.
So this is actually going to behave the same way
as if you had a unit here, and you invoked x with the parens.
Actually, you don't even need to include the parens,
I think, in Scala.
But this is actually discouraged,
like they discourage using it more than one time like this.
But it will reevaluate x every single time.
So if I do this, so I have h and I have math.random here
as my expression.
So it will actually pass this expression here.
And when x is referred to inside, it will then evaluate that.
And then when x is referred to again,
it will evaluate it again.
So that's what call by name does.
And then the results of this would
be that you get two different random values.
so you'll end up with printing out some random thing.
That's the result of that.
So remember, callByName parameters are not strict.
So we can create new control constructs
by using curried callByName functions.
So if you notice, this is a method, myWile.
and the first parameter list is a thunk that evaluates when it's called,
it will evaluate to some Boolean value.
And the other thing is a thunk that is the body that produces a unit.
So this is essentially what happens when a loop executes.
We check the condition and if the condition is true, we execute the body.
and if the condition was true, we have to go back and reevaluate the condition again, right?
So that's why you see the recursive call here.
And of course, I believe this is going to be tail recursive,
so the compiler can actually eliminate and then use the call stack.
We can eliminate stack frames.
So if you use this you can see how this looks very much like a regular old wow that we're
used to.
So here's our summary.
So we have the three kinds of argument passing.
We have call by value passing copies and the changes aren't gonna be visible to the caller.
And we have strict evaluation.
For call by reference we also have strict evaluation but we're passing lvalues as arguments.
So here we passed copies of our values, here we passed lvalues as arguments and the changes
are visible to the caller.
And here with call by name and this actually occurs in other languages besides Scala I
I just can't think of any right now,
I think Haskell probably has it.
Scala notation to pass parameterless functions as arguments.
So that's when we have no parameter, and
that's why I usually pronounce it if you have def,
foo, x,
let me just int here.
I usually, when I see this here,
it's called my name syntax, I usually say x produces a name.
That's how I think of it.
And this, so, this is non-strict evaluation.
So, these are our three ways to pass from the needs.
And now we come to the last topic tonight and it looks like we're going to fit it, just
fit it in. So we're going to talk about something called closures. So first we have to talk
about free variables. So we're going to talk about what a free variable is, we're going
to identify when a function has free variables, we're going to identify nested local methods
and functions, and we're going to describe the effect of closures. So how do free variables
get bound to variables of the environment? So we're going to talk about what all this
means.
So local variables, their scope is limited. And how does this work with functions? So
So if we have this function here, we have fact, and
we have a parameter n.
And then inside, we have another nested function and
this is actually c.
So this is bad c, it's allowed by GCC but
not by the c standard.
So c, the c standard does not allow for nested functions.
So what we have here is this nested function loop,
and we have a new variable, a new declaration of n,
and an int result, and then what we're
doing is we're doing some code here.
So this, if I actually look this up,
so nested functions GCC, we would
get to here, and this is like basically the people who implemented this compiler decided
that they were going to add this feature to the language that they were building the compiler
for.
Totally allowed, it's just not standard, right, so if you took that and tried to compile it
with some other compiler it would work.
I want to tell you that this is a bad idea.
Don't do this.
So there's a bunch of stuff here.
But what it comes down to is if you refer.
So remember when you have C code, when you exit the function,
any local storage that was created on the StackFrame
is no longer, it goes away.
So if you have inside your nested function
and you're referring to something that's on that stack frame,
then you will end up with what?
What does it mean?
So down here, if you look through this documentation,
it will say, here the function intermediate receives
the address of store as an argument.
not really looking at it. So here's the function. If intermediate calls store, so intermediate
calls store, calls this store here, oh it's passing, right it's passing the
function. The arguments given to store are used to store into array, but this technique works only
so long as the containing function hack in this example does not exit. So hack exits you lose
whatever hack is pointing to, like whatever is created on the stack for hack.
So if you try to call the nested function, this is the kicker, if you try
to call the nested function through its address, after the containing function
exits all help breaks loose. This is in the documentation of the compiler.
So if you see that as a programmer, I would be like, I'm not using that feature,
and most of my friends who are programmers that I work with would not
want to use that feature. So I caution you to think carefully about what you're doing.
So if you try to call it after a containing scope level exits and it refers to some of the variables that are no longer in scope,
you may be lucky in seeing, because maybe that data is still there,
but it's not really wise to take the risk, because you might crash.
It's like fault.
If you do this and your nested function does not refer to anything that has gone out of scope, it should be safe.
So knowing what you're doing is very important.
Anyway, so this code, you can do this in Scala, right?
In Scala, we are allowed to have nested functions.
But C is somewhat primitive, and doesn't have a solution to make this work.
Scala does, and that's going to be called a closure, so we'll talk about that.
So, here's our challenge.
So we have a typedef, which is a function pointer.
It's a function that takes an int and returns void, so that's what this means.
So f takes an int, and this is gonna end up returning.
See there's x here, and then this nested function g.
And I'm gonna print x, and I'm gonna print y, and
I'm gonna return the address of g.
So when I'm inside f and I'm executing f,
I'm gonna end up returning the address of g.
Right.
So here's my main program.
I call f and I pass 10, so my x will have 10.
And then I'm going to return the function pointer, and I'm going to store that in h1.
So now I have essentially a function I can call that was defined here in turn.
Now I'm going to dereference that and call passing 2.
And the question is, where is x?
So if I call g, so here I'm really calling g through h,
And I pass two, so here I'm going to get x is 10, y is 2.
This is unsafe call h.
It's unsafe to call h because x has already been popped, right?
I mean, it was on the stack frame, it's been popped.
And here I'm going to call the three.
So x is 20 here.
It's gonna print 20 and then it's gonna print 3 for 1.
And that's because x was 10.
So something happened.
So where is x?
So Java and Scala solve this problem.
They solve it by using this feature called closures.
So local functions in Scala in Java
actually store an environment
on the function definition.
So let's see what this means.
So here I have f, and if f is taking an int and
returning a function that takes an int and returns a unit.
And that's what println is going to be.
So when I call f, I'm going to define g,
which is going to do this printing,
then I'm going to return the function that I defined here.
And in this case, x is going to survive
and that's because we're going to pass a copy of x
into something called a closure
that is essentially the environment for g.
So this h1, if I call f with 10
and I get the function back and I start in h1
then I'm going to pass 2.
This will print 10 and y will have 2.
In this case, I'll call f with 20, and this should print with h1.
I'm still going to print, passing 3, I'm still going to print 10 because my x is still 10.
Even though I've called f again, I got a different copy of x in h2.
And now if I'm going to call h2, this time I'll print 20.
So by creating this closure and copying the data,
it's going to make it work.
In Java, this is what the Java looks like.
So this is a lot more code.
So you have a function that takes an integer and returns a void.
This is always my favorite when using this stuff, I have to return null.
I always go gross, I don't like returning null.
But that's because I've lived in Scarlet Land for so long.
So I'm invoking f passing x as an int.
And here I'm gonna construct a new, this is a lambda syntax.
I think it's,
not sure if that's a single abstract method,
I have to double check that,
but what's happening with this lambda is you're actually
constructing this new function object.
And then you're returning that object g.
And then I get that out here and I'm gonna save it in h1.
And then I'm gonna call accept,
Which is how this thing ends up getting named, passing to.
And I'll get the same results.
And then I'll do it again and I get a different instance of my function,
object, and I'll call except on h1 again.
And this will give me the same result, it'll print 10.
And here I'll call except on the second one that I created.
And this will print 20 because I passed 20 here.
So with closures, we can either copy or share.
So here's an example.
We have our outer method and our inner method.
And the outer one returns a function that takes a B and
returns a C. But it returns a function that does that.
returns a function that does that.
So our inner function takes a b and returns a c, right?
And we return the inner.
So we're returning this method here.
And the closure is going to contain the code for inner,
the code we defined for inner, and a copy of x.
Now let's add this.
added this var u and it has type A and I save my x in u and then inside here in
inner I'm going to use x and I'm going to use you and I'm going to use y and this
is all valid. What we say is that X is free, so when we talk about this X is not defined
within Inner itself. It's defined outside of Inner, it's defined in outer. So X is actually
free in here if we refer to it. And U is also free because it's not defined in Inner. Y
is going to be bound because it's a parameter on our function. So Y is going to be bound,
meaning it's defined here as part of Inter.
So we get the code for Inter and the copy of x, just like before,
but what do we do with u?
What happens with u?
And so there are a couple different options.
So one option, does Inter see an updated u?
It's a VAR, right?
It's defined outside.
So do we see an updated u?
So Scala does that.
So Scala will do that.
Could we require u to be immutable? Even though it's declared var
it's possible that we can impose a rule
Not us as Scala programmers, but if you're designing language
You can impose a rule to say that you would be immutable. Well, this is what Java does
so if you've ever seen like
Something in Java like a compiler error that says something about needing to be effectively final
That's what this is because you're you have a closure and you're closing over this u and this u has to
to be immune.
So inner has a free x, and so therefore it must have a closure.
So because inner is referring to something outside of itself,
but it's defined within the scope of the thing that is defining inner,
then you need a closure.
This is what the object-oriented implementation in Java looks like.
So what we've done here is we've sort of, somewhat contrived, but
I think under the covers this is kinda like what happens when you do that in Scala.
Remember, cuz it all runs on the JVM.
So what happens is we have this class, we'll call it closure for our discussion.
It extends abstract function.
When we call apply, that's like invoking the function.
Passing the Boolean that we're gonna take x.
So we got x when we created the closure, right.
So when we, you can think of this as when you create the closures like when you call
outer, you're defining inner, and you're creating the closure.
And then you're returning inner.
That's what happens here.
I'm returning a new closure that contains the code,
the apply code that does the work, okay.
And it also has a final reference to x, so that's what happens.
Now, in the case where we had that var u, in this case,
we have to do something like this.
We'd have to have this intref, which
refers to someplace else in memory.
So this intref we defined, I believe, on an earlier slide,
and it contained that n value, remember?
And so what I'm doing is I'm saying, okay, I'm going to construct an intref, and I'm going to have it hold a copy of x.
And then when I create my closure, I have to pass u so that u is an intref.
This is going to be final, right?
But the intref is pointing to memory that I can change, right?
So that's why this works in Scala because it does, under the covers, it does this.
So here's some examples.
So data encapsulation in a container for data and functions.
So I have, this is object oriented programming.
So if I have classes, this is like a class, an incrementor class.
It has an int i, I'm going to call this increment method which essentially takes whatever my
i is and adds x to it.
It doesn't actually update i so it's not incrementing i, it's just incrementing i by whatever.
I would almost call that increment by because that would be clearer to me.
So here I have an incrementer, it's going to contain 2 so when I construct it my i gets
And then when I call increment four it should add four plus two and
give me back six.
And then increment five it adds five plus two and gives me back seven.
Well, how do we do this in functional programming?
Well, it's as simple as this, so we have a function, sorry,
a method called incrementor.
It takes an int and returns a function.
That takes an int and returns an int.
And so here's, we're defining the function and
the function takes an x, takes an int called x and then it adds x to i,
just like we did over there.
And then I can call incrementer which gives me back a function, and
I'm gonna store that function in this thing called inc, and
now I can invoke it, right?
Inc4 gives me six, inc5 gives me seven.
So this is a lot less boilerplate to do that.
So this is useful actually for languages with strong visibility modifiers Python and JavaScript.
So now let's interpret closure.
So here's our method F. What does it initialize?
Oh sorry.
It's going to, here's the closure for, so this is the closure for a method and this
is the closure for a function.
The method is this, it's referring to this G, it's the def here.
function is referring to this thing here. So what gets initialized, I think it's what
this the point of this is it's going to be the same essentially. So this will
initialize x to minus 1 when initializing variable f. So here it's initializing this
variable f. And it will return an incremented x on every call, f, so if I
have F here I'll get that 0 oh sorry if I have F and then I invoke F I get back a
0 because it took minus 1 and incremented it. It actually in this case
it's updating, right, and then it's returning the result. And then if I do it
again I'll get one. Here's a closure for method and a closure for a function again.
So what do we got here? This time we have g of i is going to return, so g of i is
going to return a function that takes a unit and returns an int, its own z set to i.
So it's got a z here and it's going to be set to i because i...
Oh, right, here's my y, so that's an int, so I passed i in.
And so my z now gets i, right?
Same thing here.
So here my y gets bound to i.
This is actually, okay, so this is an int.
G is a function that takes an int and then, as a separate parameter,
list takes a unit and then returns an int.
It's got two of these arrows, so it's a little bit,
so it's a lot to read at 8.50 at night.
But if we look at it, g of 10, so
it's gonna take that 10, and that's going to go into y.
And then, we can now invoke h1, this is a current function, right?
So I can invoke h1, by the way,
The REPL will print out all this junk here, which is just telling you that it returned
a function.
That's why it says there.
The implementation of this is using something called nested classes which we'll talk about
next week.
So h1 and h2 will return their own incremented z, because they each have their own copy
of z.
Okay, so now we'll implement a function that prints the greeting.
So I have calling this function greeter and I'm passing a greeting and that's going to
return back a function that I can then invoke with a name and say hello to the person.
Right?
So if you look at this, this is the implementation of greeter.
So here's our greeting, and then we get back a function that
takes a name, and then splices together the greeting
and then the name.
And I guess I should say, before I go on to the right side
of there, that it will print hello, Alice, and hello, Bob.
Now over here, we have JavaScript.
So this will have event handlers with preferred preserve.
tripping over my English preserves state.
So I have a document, I get element by ID, I get the button, and
then I get the other button, button two, and then I create my greeter.
And then, right, I add an event listener.
So when I click on button one, I'll say hello Alice.
And when I click on button two I'll say hello Bob.
So this is a JavaScript example of this.
And here's the implementation of Create Greeter.
So this is an example, closure for stateful functions.
So here what I'm doing is I'm implementing a function that collects numbers and computes
our average.
So it's keeping a running average.
So cumulative average.
So I start with two, and then four, and then six.
So if I define my cumulative average function, what I'm actually doing is I'm creating in
here a mutable list buffer where I'm going to hang on to all of the inputs I ever get.
And so when somebody... I'm going to return back a function, right, and that new function
I get back is going to take an int. So that's why you see ints here, right? So when I do
that, I get... So each time I call that, I get x. And I'm adding whatever I'm passed
into my list buffer, and then I call .
And then I divide by the length, so that computes the average.
So this uses a closure, and the closure contains this data here.
It also contains implementation.
So here, here's the implement.
This is a decorator.
I don't know if anybody knows what a decorator is,
but if you've taken any software engineering courses,
it's a function that essentially does the thing
that another function does.
But it decorates it with some other behavior.
So here, the decoration is the printing frame.
So what do we got?
Well, we create cached square by calling this function
called memoize.
That's a term from algorithms, memorize.
I'm memorizing a function.
And what does this mean?
Well, I'm going to store a cache of the results.
So I'm going to return back a function that takes an X of type, capital X.
And it will actually check to see in my mutable map,
do I have a value for this key stored already?
And if I do then I'm going to get that out of the map so I don't have to do any work.
I've stored it and cached it.
If it's not there, this get or else update is going to then...
This is a non-strict so it won't actually evaluate this unless it needs to.
Right?
So if it can't find the key then it will invoke this call-by-name argument here.
function itself has a call that parameter, and you can do this in Python too,
I hate Python. So I'm not gonna heat it. So use a decorator. This is another
example, so closures for data encapsulation. So what we have here is a
function called map. Map takes an int, that's the size. So what it's essentially
So what I'm essentially doing is creating an array and
using the indexes of the array as keys.
That's why you see the int here.
So when I say get k, I'm going to check elms to see if that key,
I'm sorry I'm just gonna go to elms,
go to that spot in the array and return whatever strings are.
It might be null actually.
I believe opt-in will probably,
I don't believe it's gonna put empty strings in there.
Here, if I do a put, I'm going to update ellipsek to get v.
And then what I'm going to do is I'm actually, so this is this function map takes a size.
So I'm creating this storage in here.
So this is the closure.
This is in the closure, right?
And these functions are, these methods are in the closure.
And then, I'm returning back these functions.
This get and the put implementation.
So that's why map returns two functions.
takes an int and gives me back a string, that's get. This one is put, so this is putting the key,
whatever the int is, and the string value and returns a unit because it has this side effect
of updating the mat. Okay, so this is uh looking like a little bit of javascript,
so there's something called debouncing, which is delayed execution of a function.
So this is like, you can imagine if someone is like typing something on their browser
and you want to wait until after the typing is finished and then execute the search.
And then there's throttling.
So you would want to limit the number of executions at a time interval.
So this debouncing and throttling is another example.
It's a lot of JavaScript.
It might taste at nine o'clock.
But it's just an example.
So here's our summary.
So when we have these free variables in our nested functions, closures are necessary.
They have to get, if you think about it, they have to get the information that's needed
from somewhere.
Closures bind free variables of a function to variables from the environment, so that's
where it's getting it from somewhere, and that's the environment.
Closures align the lifetime of functions and their accessed environment.
There are closures in JavaScript.
Again, not really wanting to look closely at JavaScript tonight.
I will click the link, though, because I can actually do.
So this just brings you to a place that tells you
all about closures in JavaScript.
And that's the end, and we got to the end.
So there is a new homework assignment this week.
There's a new quiz.
The deadlines are the same usual pattern of Monday.
Flex days apply if you want one.
Make sure you message me.
I'm not traveling Monday, so.
So if you need one, I should be able to open up your,
I'm on the traveling, so I should be able to extend
your deadline if you need to.
Do you have a flight staff?
So all right, so look for emails from me and stuff in DCL
about specifics about next week's class meeting, office hours.
And we'll see how it goes.
Thank you.
So I can't do it.
This is not the case.
The price is not the case.
I'm going to give you a few minutes.
There is a couple of minutes.
I have a few minutes left.
I'm going to put a couple of minutes on this.
This is a hot sauce.
It is a hot sauce.
It is hot sauce.
It's hot sauce.
I'll see you next week.
Alright.
Have a nice day trip.
Thank you.
I will see you online next week.
Yep.
I'm going to take this long.
Thank you.
so
I'm going to take a look at this table and then I'll put it in the middle of the table.
Thank you.
And now I can step back to the next step.
I forgot to be a little later.
I didn't know that I was going to be able to get the end of the day.
If I was done, I would like to let it all be better.
I did it.
I wasn't going to be able to make it.
I just wanted to be able to make it.
I'm going to go to the next video.
I'm going to take a look at the rest of the rest of the world.
Fumou
There's no way to use it.
I'm good.
I'm not sure what's going on then.
We are ready to go.
Here, I'll use the other way to press the button on the left side.
This is all of the words that I am talking about.
Sometimes you can't use the button on the right side.
So I have to keep the button on the left side.
Thank you.
OK, so let's get started.
I'm going to wash it all with the water.
This is a busy day of work.
This is a busy day.
We are going to have a week in the morning.
I can't get a lot of fresh fruit.
I'm going to have some fresh fruit.
I'm going to have some fruit.
Alright.
Thank you.
.
I'm sorry.